

Ramona Roller

Quantitative social scientist

H

15 December 1991



Weinbergstrasse 56/58, Switzerland



https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/people/rroller/



rroller@ethz.ch

About me -

Social scientist with a strong quantitative background. Fascinated by complex systems and their mathematical descriptions. Currently working on reconstruction methods for historical letter correspondence networks. Future aim: Develop spatio-temporal null models for historical letter correspondence networks.

Skill Python

Social network analysis

Socio-historical data analysis

Data visualisation

Agent-based modeling

(*)[The skill scale is from 0 (Fundamental Awareness) to 5 (Expert).]

Education

since 01/2018 Ph.D. candidate in data-driven modeling

of social systems

ETH Zurich, CH

• Develop quantitative statistical methods to analyse socio-

• Develop quantitative statistical methods to analyse sociohistorical data.

Construct and visualise temporal network models.

• Expected graduation: November 2021.

09/2018 Participant at EPFL's Reproducibility in Computational Science
Summer School Magliaso, CH

Acquired profound skills in writing reproducible research papers

and data management. Specific tools include Git, R Shiny, and

Renga.

09/2015 - 12/2017 M.Sc. Computational Science University of Amsterdam. NL

• Thesis: Optimising Resource Allocation in Socio-economic Systems with the Minority Game: A Case Study on Electric Cars in

Amsterdam.

06/2017 - 07/2017 Participant at SFI's Complex Systems Summer School Santa Fe

Institute, USA

Passed highly competitive world-wide application process.

• Deepened numerical and computational methods for the anal-

ysis of complex systems.

10/2011 - 07/2014 B.Sc. Psychology with Cognitive Science University of Sussex, UK

• Thesis: Differences between conscious and unconscious learn-

ing of social rules.

Research and Work Experience

11/2014 - 06/2015 Intern at Netherlands Organisation for

Applied Scientific Research (TNO)

Soesterberg, NL

• Developed a Linked Data model to cope with power cuts caused

by flooding.

• Applied qGIS to visualise power stations and water levels.

06/2013 - 06/2014

Junior research associate at Department of Informatics University of Sussex, UK

• Developed a novel method to quantify and visualise cognitive chunks based on the sequences of participants' drawings of elec-

trical circuit diagrams.

Publications

 Roller, R, 2021: Vectorizing maps to generate geo-spatial data on territories of the Holy Roman Empire. socarxiv. doi=10.31235/osf.io/y9v68.

Conference attendances and research visits

03/2021 Geography meets Digital Humanities: Neuere Ansätze raumbe-

zogener Modellierung

Erlangen (online), DE

• Talk: 'Räumliche Aspekte der Konfessionalisierung: Vektorisierte Territorien des HRR erstellen und nutzen'.

• Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_roller/data/2020-03-12_Erlangen.pdf

10/2020

Theorytellings Workshop der DHd AG Theorie

Leipzig, DE

• Talk: 'Warum wurde Luther protestantisch? Erklärungsnarrative mit statistischen Modellen entwickeln und zur Theoriebildung nutzen'.

• Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_roller/data/2020-10-09_Leipzig.pdf

09/2019 European Conference on Social Network Analysis (EUSN) Zurich, CH • Talk: 'Statistical inference for letter network of Reformation'. Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_ roller/data/2019-09-11_ Zurich. pdf 07/2019 International Conference on Computational Social Science (IC^2S^2) Amsterdam, NL Talk: 'Network regression reveals factors driving the letter correspondence of 16th century reformers'. Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_ roller/data/2019-07-18_ Amsterdam. pdf 06/2019 Research visit at Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities Vienna, AU Enlarged skills on vectorisation of raster maps and management of spatial data. Talk: 'A workflow for automated vectorisation of raster maps'. Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_ roller/data/2019-06-17_ Vienna. pdf 01/2019 Research Visit at Heidelberg Academy of Sciences and Humani-• Talk: 'Das Briefkorrespondenznetzwerk der Reformatoren'. Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_ roller/data/2019-01-21_Heidelberg.pdf Organisation of scientific events since 01/2021 Co-organiser of the workshop 'Opportunities in computerised analyses of historical letter correspondences' • Teamed-up with project 'Theologenbriefwechsel im Südwesten des Reichs in der Frühen Neuzeit (1550-1620) led by Prof. Strohm in Heidelberg. • Organised talks, discussion groups and accomodations for 30 participants. · Speakers include international researchers from the humanities, computer- and data sciences. Planned date: Spring 2022 06/2018 Co-organiser and participant at Big Data in the Field Weekend · Organised talks, workshops, discussion rounds, and accommodation for 50 participants and 6 speakers. • Speakers included German Data Science professors and representatives of German companies that apply Big Data-based technologies. Awards 01/2020 Travel grant for DHd conference (Digital Humanities im deutschsprachigen Raum) 02/2012 - 12/2017 Member of German National Academic Foundation Stuart Sutherland Prize for an outstanding undergraduate dis-07/2014

sertation in psychology at the University of Sussex

CUDAN Satellite at NetSci

Talk: 'Letter network to test theory'.

roller/data/2020-09-11_Rome.pdf

Digital Humanities im deutschsprachigen Raum

roller/data/2020-03-05_Paderborn.pdf

znetzwerk der Reformatoren? Eine Netzwerkanalyse'.

Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_

Talk: 'Wie steuert geografische Distanz das Briefkorresponden-

Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_

Rome (online), IT

Paderborn, DE

09/2020

03/2020